Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听 EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是 Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're tackling a very difficult issue for many English learners.
我是 Catherine，今天我们讨论一个很多英语学习者觉得棘手的问题。
We're talking about taking things from other people and giving them back.
我们要聊的是从别人那里拿东西再还回去。
That's right.
没错。
So today we are going to talk about money and we're going to lend money and borrow money
所以今天我们要谈钱，我们会讨论借钱和贷款。
and we're going to talk more about this after we listen to the dialogue.
听完对话后，我们再详细聊聊这个话题。
Can I borrow five bucks?
能借我五块钱吗？
No.
不行。
Come on.
别这样嘛。
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
我周二还你。
Last time I lent you money you never paid me back.
上次我借钱给你，你根本没还。
I promise if you lend me five dollars today I will repay you in full next week.
我保证，如果你今天借我五美元，我下周全额还你。
Okay.
好吧。
But I'm taking your skateboard as collateral.
但我要拿你的滑板当抵押品。
Fine.
行。
I can't believe you don't trust me.
真不敢相信你不信任我。
It's nothing personal.
这不是针对你。
Just business.
只是公事公办。
All right.
好吧。
So now let's take a look at that language on Language Takeaway.
现在让我们看看“语言要点”部分的内容。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
So first up we have the key verbs for today.
首先，我们今天的关键动词。
The verb to borrow and to lend.
动词“借入”和“借出”。
Now this is a really important difference to make because many people make this mistake
这是一个非常重要的区别，因为很多人会犯错误。
where they use the wrong verb.
用错动词。
Now if I ask you Marco, can I borrow your bicycle?
如果我问你 Marco，我能借你的自行车吗？
That means can I take your bicycle from you and then later I'll give it back.
意思是，我能从你那里拿走自行车，然后稍后还给你。
But I want to use it.
但我想用它。
Right.
对。
So the verb is kind of reflexive.
所以这个动词有点反身性。
It's going on to you.
它指向你。
You want to borrow.
你想借。
I want to borrow.
我想借。
I want to take it from you for a short time and then I want to give it back.
我想从你那里暂时拿走，然后还回去。
So to borrow.
所以是“借入”。
Now the other verb is to lend and that on the other hand goes from me to you.
另一个动词是“借出”，它从我这到你那。
So you borrow my bicycle.
所以你借我的自行车。
I lend you my bicycle.
我借给你我的自行车。
I give it to you.
我把它给你。
That's right.
没错。
So another way of asking can I borrow is can you lend me your bike?
所以另一种问“我能借吗”的方式是“你能借给我你的自行车吗？”
That means can you act?
意思是，你能行动吗？
Can you do this thing for me?
你能为我做这件事吗？
So there's two different ways of saying it and it's very important to remember who is
所以有两种不同的说法，记住谁在做什么非常重要。
doing what.
做什么。
Exactly.
完全正确。
So remember the person taking is borrowing.
所以记住，拿东西的人是“借入”。
The person giving is lending.
给东西的人是“借出”。
So it's not correct to say can you borrow me your bicycle?
所以不能说“你能借给我你的自行车吗？”
That's not right.
那不对。
No.
不。
Can you lend me?
你能借给我吗？
Like can you lend me a hand?
比如“你能帮我一把吗？”
Can you help me?
你能帮我吗？
Right.
对。
So remember this.
所以记住这个。
To borrow is something I do.
“借入”是我做的事。
I want to borrow from you.
我想从你那里借。
It's the person, the subject in a sentence.
它是句子中的主语。
But in the case of lending, someone else is doing it.
但在“借出”的情况下，是别人在做。
So can you lend to me or can you lend it to him?
所以“你能借给我吗”或“你能借给他吗？”
You have to say who it's being lent to.
你必须说明借给谁。
Exactly.
完全正确。
And as you said who it's being lent to.
正如你所说，要说明借给谁。
So the past tense of lend is lent.
所以“借出”的过去式是“lent”。
Yeah.
是的。
So Marco lent me his bike last week and I broke it.
所以 Marco 上周借给我他的自行车，我把它弄坏了。
So now I have to pay him a lot of money.
所以现在我必须赔他很多钱。
You have to pay me five bucks and that's our next word, bucks.
你得赔我五块钱，这就是我们的下一个词，“bucks”。
Bucks.
“Bucks”。
Now this is a slang term.
这是一个俚语。
So this is something we say very casually in America when we want to talk about dollars.
在美国，当我们想谈论美元时，这是一个很随意的说法。
So one buck is one dollar.
所以一“buck”就是一美元。
A hundred bucks is a hundred dollars.
一百“bucks”就是一百美元。
All right.
好的。
Now as you said it's very American.
正如你所说，这很美国化。
You wouldn't really use it like, I don't know if you're in Britain, you wouldn't say a hundred
你不会真的用它，比如，我不知道如果你在英国，你不会说一百“bucks”。
bucks.
“bucks”。
No, you would say quid.
不，你会说“quid”。
Quid.
英镑。
Yeah, exactly.
对，没错。
So they don't have dollars so they don't say bucks.
所以他们不用美元，也就不说“bucks”。
Not in England.
在英国不是这样。
All right.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
So we wanted to borrow five dollars and that person promised to pay you back on Tuesday.
所以我们想借五美元，那个人答应周二还你。
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
我周二还你钱。
All right.
好的。
So this is a lot like that verb to lend.
这跟动词“lend”很像。
To lend him, to pay you, you have to say who you're going to pay, right?
借给他、还给你，你得说清楚要还给谁，对吧？
So Marco, I'm sorry about your bicycle.
所以，Marco，关于你的自行车我很抱歉。
I will pay you back tomorrow.
我明天还你钱。
Okay.
好的。
That means I will give you money for it tomorrow.
意思是明天我会给你钱补偿。
So if you borrow money, you have to pay it back.
所以如果你借钱，就得还钱。
All right.
好的。
So I want to borrow five dollars.
所以我想借五美元。
I promise I will pay you back Thursday.
我保证周四还你。
Very good.
很好。
Okay.
好的。
So now lastly, we will lend money, but of course we need a guarantee.
最后，我们会借钱，但当然需要担保。
We need something to make sure that you will pay me back.
我们需要一些东西来确保你会还我钱。
So that's called collateral.
这就叫抵押品。
All right.
好的。
Now collateral is important because sometimes you can't trust someone, like you say, Marco.
抵押品很重要，因为有时候你不能信任别人，就像你说的，Marco。
And so for example, if I want to rent a bicycle, so I want to use it for the day, maybe there's
比如，如果我想租一辆自行车，用一天，可能有个
a store that they rent bicycles to people.
商店出租自行车给人们。
I would give my passport or my driver's license as collateral because I will definitely return
我会把护照或驾照作为抵押品，因为我肯定会回来
to take my driver's license or passport back.
取回我的驾照或护照。
So that's basically a sign of a promise, money or identification or some object.
所以这基本上是一种承诺的象征，可以是钱、身份证明或某个物品。
That's right.
没错。
So usually, for example, if you're going to get a very big loan at the bank, they will
所以通常，比如，如果你要从银行贷一大笔款，他们会
ask you for something as collateral.
要求你提供一些东西作为抵押品。
So maybe you will have to give them your house as collateral.
所以你可能得把房子作为抵押品。
So you're saying if I can't pay you back, then you can take my house.
所以你是说，如果我还不了钱，你就可以拿走我的房子。
That's right.
没错。
So collateral is the last word in language takeaway, but we do have some great phrases
所以“抵押品”是语言总结的最后一个词，但我们还有一些很棒的短语
for you coming up in Fluency Builder.
在流利度训练中要介绍给你。
Can I borrow five bucks?
能借我五块钱吗？
No.
不行。
Come on.
别这样。
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
我周二还你。
Last time I lent you money, you never paid me back.
上次我借钱给你，你一直没还。
I promise if you lend me five dollars today, I will repay you in full next week.
我保证如果你今天借我五美元，我下周全额还你。
OK, but I'm taking your skateboard as collateral.
好吧，但我拿你的滑板当抵押品。
Fine.
行。
I can't believe you don't trust me.
真不敢相信你不信任我。
It's nothing personal, just business.
这不是针对个人，只是公事公办。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So let's take a look at these phrases on Fluency Builder.
让我们看看流利度训练中的这些短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
So, Marco, these are two friends talking and the way they talk to each other is very casual,
所以，Marco，这是两个朋友在聊天，他们说话的方式很随意，
so we hear at the beginning, can I borrow five bucks?
所以我们一开始听到“能借我五块钱吗？”
No.
不行。
Come on.
别这样。
Right.
对。
So what is this?
这是什么意思？
Come on.
别这样。
It's a persuasive phrase.
这是一个说服性的短语。
It's one of those phrases where you're trying to convince or persuade people and you can
这是那种你试图说服或劝服别人时用的短语，在很多情况下
use it as an interjection in many situations.
都可以用作感叹词。
So for example, here, come on, lend it to me.
比如，这里，“别这样，借给我吧。”
Lend me some money.
借我点钱。
I'll pay you back.
我会还你的。
You're trying to convince that person.
你在试图说服那个人。
Please.
求你了。
Yeah, exactly.
对，没错。
But what about this situation?
但这种情况呢？
I'm running late.
我要迟到了。
I have to go and my friend, she's still sitting at her desk, maybe at work and it's taking
我得走了，我的朋友还坐在办公桌前，可能在工作，而且她
forever.
拖了很久。
I say, come on, let's go.
我说，“快点，我们走吧。”
Right.
对。
It's like, hurry up, move it.
就像“快点，动起来。”
All right.
好的。
So it's a way of getting someone to do something.
所以这是一种让别人做某事的方式。
You want them to follow you.
你想让他们跟着你。
Exactly.
没错。
And now talking about money again, the person promised to repay the money.
现在又说到钱，那个人承诺会还钱。
He said, I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
他说，我星期二还你钱。
But then he also said, I will repay you in full next week.
但接着他又说，我下周全额还你。
In full.
全额。
Now, remember, this is important.
现在，记住，这点很重要。
I will repay you in full.
我会全额还你。
That means I won't repay you a little bit and then a little bit later.
这意味着我不会先还一点，再还一点。
I will repay you everything next week.
我下周会一次性还清所有钱。
Right, exactly.
对，没错。
So if you have to pay or repay someone in full, you have to give them the entire amount,
所以，如果你必须全额支付或偿还某人，你得给他们全部金额，
not just a part of it.
而不是只还一部分。
That's right.
没错。
In full.
全额。
Full means everything.
全额就是全部。
The final phrase is the very last line of today's dialogue.
最后一个短语是今天对话的最后一句。
It's nothing personal.
这不是针对个人。
It's just business.
这只是生意。
I think this is a common phrase that people use when maybe doing business with friends
我觉得这是人们跟朋友做生意时常用的一个短语，
or people you know.
或者跟认识的人。
Maybe you're asking for collateral and the guy's like, I can't believe you don't trust
也许你要求抵押品，对方会说，我真不敢相信你不信任
me.
我。
I'm your brother.
我是你兄弟。
And he's like, it's nothing personal.
然后你说，这不是针对个人。
It's just business.
这只是生意。
It's a way to say, listen, this is not about you and me.
这是一种说法，意思是，听着，这不关你我的事。
This is about my rules.
这关乎我的规矩。
And when I give something to someone, I always ask for collateral.
当我借东西给别人时，我总是要求抵押品。
So it's just business.
所以这只是生意。
It's just my way of doing this.
这只是我做事的方式。
Exactly.
没错。
So it's a good phrase to use if you're doing maybe business with a friend.
所以如果你跟朋友做生意，这是个好用的短语。
And of course, maybe you're setting these rules and maybe your friend feels a little
当然，也许你定下这些规矩，你的朋友会觉得有点
bit offended.
被冒犯。
You say, hey, it's nothing personal.
你就说，嘿，这不是针对个人。
It's just business.
这只是生意。
Nothing personal.
不是针对个人。
So that's the last phrase.
这就是最后一个短语。
Let's take a listen to the dialogue again and we'll be right back.
让我们再听一遍对话，我们马上回来。
Can I borrow five bucks?
能借我五块钱吗？
No.
不行。
Come on.
别这样。
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
我星期二还你。
Last time I lent you money, you never paid me back.
上次我借你钱，你一直没还。
I promise if you lend me five dollars today, I will repay you in full next week.
我保证如果你今天借我五美元，我下周全额还你。
OK, but I'm taking your skateboard as collateral.
好吧，但我拿你的滑板当抵押品。
Fine.
行。
I can't believe you don't trust me.
我真不敢相信你不信任我。
It's nothing personal.
这不是针对个人。
Just business.
只是生意。
All right.
好吧。
So lending money, borrowing money.
所以，借钱，还钱。
Now, as we mentioned, sometimes you have people that ask you for money.
现在，正如我们提到的，有时候会有人向你借钱。
Now, did you ever have that friend that always asked you for money and never repaid you?
你有没有遇到过那种总是向你借钱却从不还的朋友？
Yes.
有。
Like a dollar at a time.
就像一次一美元。
Hey, can I borrow a dollar?
嘿，能借我一美元吗？
Can I borrow five dollars?
能借我五美元吗？
Yeah, always.
是啊，总是这样。
And actually this friend, he would borrow ten dollars and he'd say, oh, I'll buy you
实际上这个朋友，他会借十美元，然后说，哦，我明天请你喝
a coffee tomorrow.
杯咖啡。
I say, what, a ten dollar coffee?
我说，什么，十美元的咖啡？
I don't think so.
我才不信。
So it was always uneven.
所以总是不对等。
And I paid more and he never repaid me in full.
我付得更多，他从来没全额还过我。
Right.
对。
So, yeah.
所以，是啊。
And actually, I think if you add up all those little that little amount of money that maybe
实际上，我觉得如果你把那些朋友可能借走的小钱加起来，
some friends borrowed from you, it would be quite a decent amount.
会是一笔不小的数目。
I had many friends who would be like, hey, can I borrow a dollar or, you know, even like
我有很多朋友会这样，嘿，能借我一美元吗，或者甚至一次
25 cents at a time.
25美分。
It would add up over time.
时间长了就会累积起来。
After a couple of years.
几年之后。
Yeah, that's that's like a whole dinner.
是啊，那就像一顿饭钱了。
Exactly.
没错。
So what do you call these people?
那么这种人叫什么？
The word in English that's a slang word is called a mooch.
英语里有个俚语词叫“蹭客”。
A mooch.
蹭客。
He's a mooch.
他是个蹭客。
It means he's always taking money from people or asking other people to pay for his dinner
意思是他总是从别人那里拿钱，或者让别人付他的晚餐，
or staying at someone's house.
或者住在别人家。
So a mooch is someone who tries to get things for free.
所以蹭客就是那种想白拿东西的人。
Right.
没错。
That's exactly it.
就是这样。
I had friends like this that would for food as well.
我也有这样的朋友，他们会蹭吃的。
Like maybe I brought my lunch.
比如我带了午餐。
This is in school, obviously.
这当然是在学校的时候。
And they would mooch off me like half my sandwich or half my juice.
他们会蹭我一半的三明治或一半的果汁。
Can I have some chips?
我能吃点薯片吗？
Can I have some juice?
我能喝点果汁吗？
Yeah, exactly.
对，就是这样。
So that's the mooch behavior.
这就是蹭吃蹭喝的行为。
So that's the verb to mooch off someone.
所以动词是“to mooch off someone”。
Yeah, to mooch off someone.
对，就是“to mooch off someone”。
But it's also a noun.
但它也是名词。
He's a mooch.
他是个蹭吃蹭喝的人。
Very interesting stuff.
挺有意思的。
Maybe you have a friend that was a mooch or maybe even yourself back in the day.
也许你有个朋友是蹭吃蹭喝的人，或者你自己以前也是。
So let us know how it works in your country.
所以告诉我们你们国家的情况。
If you lend money to people, family members, do you ask for collateral?
如果你借钱给别人，比如家人，你会要求抵押吗？
Or do you just forget about it?
还是干脆就算了？
Let us know.
告诉我们吧。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是EnglishPod.com。
We'll see you guys there.
我们会在那里见你们。
Bye.
再见。